# oritz Reuss

🛘 (+49) 15122035375 | 🔀 moritz.reuss@kit.edu | 🏕 mbreuss.github.io | 🖸 mbreuss | 🛅 moritzreuss

### Research Interest

My primary research goal is to build intelligent embodied agents that assist people in their everyday lives and communicate intuitively. One of the key challenges to be solved towards this goal is learning from multimodal, uncurated human demonstrations without rewards. Therefore, I am working on novel methods that exploit multimodality and learn versatile behaviour, as demonstrated in my work on Score-based Diffusion Policies.

### **Education**

**Ph.D in Computer Science** 

Karlsruhe, Germany

KARLSRUHE INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY (KIT)

01/2022 - Present

03/2019 - 09/2021

· Supervised by Prof. Rudolf Lioutikov

Karlsruhe, Germany

**MSc in Mechanical Engineering** KARLSRUHE INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY (KIT)

• GPA: 1.3 (on scale of 1-5 with 1 being the highest score)

Exchange Semester at Chalmers University of Technology, Sweden - 2020/21

**BSc in Mechanical Engineering** 

Karlsruhe, Germany

KARLSRUHE INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY (KIT)

10/2015 - 02/2019

• GPA: 2.0 (on scale of 1-5 with 1 being the highest score)

**German A-Levels** Barcelona, Spain

GERMAN SCHOOL OF BARCELONA

2015

• GPA: 1.2 (on scale of 1-6 with 1 being the highest score)

Graduated as Top of the Year with distinction.

# **Work Experience**

### **Graduate Research Assistant**

Karlsruhe, Germany

KARLSRUHE INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY (KIT)

01/2022 - Present

- Introduced a novel imitation learning policy, called 'Score-based Diffusion Policies', to learn expressive, multimodal behavior from offline data.
- Proposed a scalable transformer-based architecture and auxiliary objectives for the diffusion policy to learn language-guided behavior from multimodal reward specifications.
- Developing a novel algorithm for zero-shot annotation of uncurated demonstrations with vision-language foundation models.

**Master Thesis Candidate** Renningen, Germany

**BOSCH CORPORATE RESEARCH** 

04/2021 - 09/2021

- Research on hybrid models for control, combining recurrent neural networks with physic-based models for precise inverse dynamics prediction in a 7-DoF robotic arm, enhancing impedance control capabilities.
- · Devised a fully-differentiable formulation of barycentric parameters, inherently ensuring compliance with all physical constraints.
- Successfully implemented and tested the hybrid model in real-time impedance control on a Franka robot arm using C++ and ROS.

### **Student Research Assistant**

Karlsruhe, Germany

RESEARCH CENTER FOR INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY (FZI)

05/2019 - 02/2021

- · Conducted research in energy consumption models for electric vehicles using recurrent neural networks, such as LSTMs and Transformers, effectively leveraging supplemental road information data in Tensorflow.
- Designed and implemented a Python framework for efficient data extraction and preprocessing, enhancing EV driving range estimation with contextual weather, traffic and road data.

### **Student Intern and Bachelor Thesis Candidate**

Neckarsulm, Germany

04/2018 - 01/2019

- Bachelor Thesis project on using dimension-less parameters models for predicting the air humidity in hydrogen fuel-cell cars in real-time.
- Functional development for optimizing the control of pressure systems in hydrogen fuel-cell systems.

**Student Intern** IPG-AUTOMOTIVE GMBH Karlsruhe, Germany

10/2016 - 03/2018

- · Executed a V2X demonstrator in CarMaker and Matlab, with additional research in hybrid drive architectures and tire models.
- Specialized in powertrain parameterization for hybrid vehicles and digitalization of real-world routes for fuel-consumption investigations.

MORITZ REUSS · CV JUNE 18, 2024

### **Publications**

- Scaling Robot Policy Learning via Zero-Shot Labeling with Foundation Models
   Nils Blank, Moritz Reuss, Fabian Wenzel, Oier Mees, Rudolf Lioutikov.
   under review, Spotlight Presentation at the 2nd Workshop on Mobile Manipulation and Embodied Intelligence at ICRA 2024.
- Multimodal Diffusion Transformer: Learning Versatile Behavior from Multimodal Goals Moritz Reuss, Ömer Erdinç Yağmurlu, Fabian Wenzel, Rudolf Lioutikov. RSS, 2024.
- Efficient Diffusion Transformer Policies with Mixture of Expert Denoisers for Multitask Learning Moritz Reuss\*, Jyothish Pari\*, Pulkit Agrawal, Rudolf Lioutikov. under review, ICRA 2024 Workshop: A Future Roadmap for Sensorimotor Skill Learning for Robot Manipulation.
- Towards Diverse Behaviors: A Benchmark for Imitation Learning with Human Demonstrations
  Xiaogang Jia, Denis Blessing, Xinkai Jiang, Moritz Reuss, Atalay Donat, Rudolf Lioutikov, Gerhard Neumann.
  ICLR, 2024.
- Goal-Conditioned Imitation Learning Using Score-based Diffusion Policies
  Moritz Reuss, Maximilian Li, Xiaogang Jia, Rudolf Lioutikov.

  RSS, 2023. under review at IJRR, Best Paper Award at the Workshop on Learning from Diverse, Offline Data (L-DOD) @ ICRA 2023.
- Information Maximizing Curriculum: A Curriculum-Based Approach for Learning Versatile Skills Denis Blessing, Onur Celik, Xiaogang Jia, Moritz Reuss, Maximilian Li, Rudolf Lioutikov, Gerhard Neumann. *NeurIPS*, 2023.
- End-to-End Learning of Hybrid Inverse Dynamics Models for Precise and Compliant Motion Tracking Moritz Reuss, Niels van Duijkeren, Robert Krug, Philipp Becker, Vaisakh Shaj, Gerhard Neumann. *RSS*, 2022.

# **Teaching**

#### **Advanced Artificial Intelligence**

Teaching Assistant

KARLSRUHE INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY

SS 2024

### **Explainable Artificial Intelligence**

Teaching Assistant

KARLSRUHE INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY

SS 2023

# **Community Support**

### Reviewing

- Conference on Robot Learning (CoRL)
- Robotics: Science and Systems (RSS)
- Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS)
- Transactions on Machine Learning Research (TMLR)
- IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA)
- IEEE Robotics and Automation Letters (RA-L)

#### **Open Source Contributions**

• diffusion-literature-for-robotics Created a comprehensive guide on diffusion models for robotics, regularly updated, to support research and learning in the field.

## **Skills**

**Language** German (native), English (fluent), Spanish (B1), French (B1) **Machine Learning** Pytorch, MuJoCo, Numpy, Pandas, Scipy, Tensorflow, JAX

Programming Python, Matlab, Docker, Git, ROS, C++
Other MFX, Linux–Ubuntu, Microsoft Office